Heaven has called for him.
Surga telah memanggilnya.
What we have here is nothing more than Richard Braun's empty body.
Yang ada di sini hanyalah raga tak berjiwa Richard Braun.
His soul will live on forever.
Jiwanya akan hidup selamanya.
Let us swear an oath on his soul
Mari berjanji demi mendiang Richard
to continue living on with hope.
untuk terus hidup penuh harapan.
In Psalms 23 of the Bible…
Pada Alkitab, Kitab Mazmur 23…
This is hard to bear.
Aku tidak tega.
What a lonely funeral.
Pemakaman yang sepi.
He was such an outstanding detective,
Padahal dia detektif yang luar biasa,
yet not a single person from the police came to attend.
tak ada satu pun rekan polisi yang datang.
His alcoholism caused problems when he was in the force,
Kecanduannya pada alkohol memicu masalah di kepolisian,
and he fell to his death in a drunken stupor.
dan dia tewas terjatuh saat teler.
That's what the police say.
Itu kata polisi.
The day after he died,
Di hari kematiannya,
he apparently had plans to meet with his daughter.
dia punya rencana untuk bertemu dengan putrinya.
What… What have I done for him?
Apa… Apa yang kuperbuat?
Dr. Reichwein.
Dr. Reichwein.
Did I really just sit in my chair, listen to him talk,
Aku cuma duduk di kursiku, mendengarkannya bicara,
and say, "You've made a full recovery"?
dan menyebutnya sudah sembuh.
What is it that I've done for him?
Apa ini gara-gara perbuatanku?
Dr. Tenma.
Dokter Tenma?
If we can find him, we might be able to solve everything.
Jika kita bisa menemukannya, mungkin kasus bisa dipecahkan.
Dr. Tenma…
Dokter Tenma.
Doesn't it seem strange, Doctor?
Ini aneh, 'kan, Dok?
This was no mere accident.
Ini bukan kecelakaan.
Nor was it a suicide.
Juga bukan bunuh diri.
Richard talked to his daughter only a few hours before his death,
Beberapa jam sebelum tewas, Richard bicara dengan putrinya di telepon
with plans to meet the next day.
dan janji bertemu esoknya.
Doctor, you did what you could.
Dok, kau sudah berjuang semaksimal mungkin.
And Richard had made a wonderful recovery.
Richard juga pulih dari kecanduannya.
Please stop blaming yourself.
Tolong jangan menyalahkan dirimu.
And then…
Lalu…
Listen to this, Doctor.
Dengarkan ini, Dok.
Ever since my husband was caught cheating,
Sejak suamiku tepergok selingkuh,
he won't say a word to me.
dia tak mau bicara padaku.
Day after day, he washes his car and tidies up the yard after that.
Tiap hari, dia mencuci mobil, lalu merapikan taman.
We won't even look at me.
Sama sekali tak menatapku.
I mean, it's better than him not coming home at all,
Yah, itu lebih baik daripada tak pulang sama sekali,
but I'll go crazy going through this every day.
tapi aku stres mengalaminya tiap hari.
Huh? Are you listening, Doctor?
Dr. Reichwein mendengarkan, tidak?
What? Oh, yes.
Apa? Ya.
Please continue.
Silakan lanjutkan.
So then, I marched into the home of that woman he slept with.
Lalu, aku melabrak rumah selingkuhannya.
And guess what happened, Doctor?
Coba tebak yang terjadi, Dok.
Criminal intent?
Pembunuhan?
There was none.
Bukan.
That was simply an accident.
Itu cuma kecelakaan.
That night, Richard Braun
Malam itu, Richard Braun
went up the rooftop of Munich University Building 12 on his own,
naik ke atap Gedung 12 Universitas München sendirian,
downed a bottle of whiskey,
menenggak sebotol wiski,
and fell to his death in a drunken stupor.
lalu jatuh dari atap karena teler.
Did you properly look into the bottle?
Botolnya sudah dianalisis?
We did.
Sudah.
We found Richard's fingerprints.
Kami menemukan sidik jari Richard.
Can you show me that bottle?
Boleh kulihat botolnya?
Well, I guess I could.
Mungkin boleh.
But it's in pieces.
Tapi sudah pecah.
Richard…
Richard.
Doesn't it seem strange?
Ini aneh, 'kan?
Richard talked to his daughter only a few hours before his death,
Beberapa jam sebelum tewas, Richard bicara dengan putrinya di telepon
with plans to meet the next day.
dan janji bertemu esoknya.
Yeah, this guy was definitely in this bar that night.
Ya, pria ini memang kemari malam itu.
Was he alone?
Dia sendirian?
Well, I don't remember.
Aku tidak ingat.
You remember him coming here, but you don't remember if he came alone?
Kau ingat dia kemari, tapi tak ingat sendirian atau tidak?
I mean, he ordered a coffee.
Habis, dia memesan kopi.
Coffee?
Kopi?
It's rare for customers to come here at that hour and not drink alcohol.
Jarang-jarang pembeli ke bar larut malam tanpa minum alkohol.
I don't suppose he was with this young man when he came?
Saat kemari, apa dia bersama pemuda ini?
I'm not sure.
Entahlah.
Try to remember.
Coba ingat-ingat.
I don't know.
Aku tak tahu.
We have tons of customers coming in and out.
Banyak pembeli keluar masuk.
But it's true that he bought whiskey.
Tapi dia memang membeli wiski.
It's written on the bill.
Ada di tagihannya.
Was Richard really the one who bought it?
Benarkah Richard yang membelinya?
I told you, I don't remember.
Sudah kubilang, aku tak ingat.
The bill just says "one bottle of Racke" on it.
Di notanya tertulis "satu botol Racke".
What did you just say?
Kau bilang apa barusan?
One bottle of Racke.
Satu botol Racke.
Why didn't the police notice when they saw the label on the bottle?
Kenapa polisi tak sadar saat melihat labelnya di botol?
What?
Apa?
Drinking again?
Minum lagi?
Well, I mean, just a little.
Yah, cuma sedikit.
What did you drink?
Kau minum apa?
Whiskey.
Wiski.
I only stick with whiskey.
Aku cuma minum wiski.
I bet your room stinks of Racke.
Pasti kamarmu bau Racke.
Racke? You must be kidding me.
Racke? Yang benar saja.
I'd never drink that domestic crap.
Aku tak pernah beli produk lokal murahan.
It has to be authentic Scotch.
Aku beli wiski Scotch asli.
It's a rule of mine.
Itu harus.
Richard isn't the one who bought that whiskey.
Bukan Richard yang membeli wiski itu.
Johan.
Johan.
It must be him after all.
Pasti dia.
Wait!
Tunggu!
Hold it right there!
Jangan kabur!
Hey.
Hei.
What do you want?
Ada apa?
Why did you try to push me?
Kenapa kau mencoba mendorongku?
Who cares? What are you talking about?
Enak saja. Apa maksudmu?
Stop playing dumb!
Jangan pura-pura!
Hey, gramps.
Hei, Kakek.
Do you have business with my buddy here?
Ada urusan dengan temanku?
-Take this! -Yeah!
- Rasakan ini! - Ya!
Drop dead, gramps!
Mati kau, Kek!
There!
Nih!
Who asked you to do this?
Kalian disuruh siapa?
Act your age.
Ingat umur.
An old man like you should be quietly taking care of his grandkids.
Kakek-kakek mestinya mengasuh cucu saja.
Hey, wait right there!
Hei, tunggu!
What?
Apa?
Wait!
Tunggu!
I trained with the border police.
Aku dilatih oleh polisi perbatasan.
Why did you try to push me?
Kenapa kau mencoba mendorongku?
I don't know anything about that.
Aku tak tahu itu.
Don't underestimate a former police surgeon.
Jangan remehkan mantan dokter polisi!
I was asked to do it.
Aku disuruh.
By who?
Siapa?
By a huge man.
Pria besar.
A huge man?
Pria besar?
A guy I passed by in the metro passageway handed me money
Ada pria lewat di lorong metro yang memberiku uang
and said to push you off.
dan menyuruhku mendorongmu.
I bought this for you, Richard.
Kubelikan untukmu, Richard.
It's authentic Scotch.
Ini wiski Scotch asli.
You wanted some, right?
Kau ingin minum ini, 'kan?
It's fine now.
Sekarang tak apa.
Drink as much as you want.
Minumlah sepuasmu.
Richard, leave it to me.
Richard, serahkan kepadaku.
I will figure it out.
Akan kubongkar.
That man's…
Kedoknya.
Johan's true form.
Wujud asli Johan.
So then, Doctor, I gave my husband a piece of my mind.
Terus, aku mengomeli suamiku.
I told him his infidelity is like an illness.
Kubilang ketidaksetiaannya itu penyakit.
And I said he should get counseling from you too.
Kusuruh dia konseling denganmu.
Doctor, are you listening?
Dok, dengar, tidak?
What? Oh, of course, Mrs. Hesse.
Apa? Tentu saja, Bu Hesse.
What do you think?
Apa pendapatmu?
With the way he is now,
Kalau suamiku begini terus,
my depression just keeps getting worse.
depresiku akan terus memburuk.
Well, you don't really have depression.
Ibu tak mengidap depresi.
What?
Apa?
I'm more worried about your husband,
Aku lebih mencemaskan suamimu,
who silently spends every day washing his car and tidying the yard.
yang seharian mencuci mobil dan menata taman tanpa bicara.
Right?
Ya, 'kan?
It's strange, no matter how you look at it.
Bagaimanapun, itu aneh.
Please, Doctor.
Kumohon, Dok.
Can you take a look at him?
Bisakah kau menemuinya?
Sure.
Bisa.
Yes, I should be free the day after tomorrow at 5:00 p.m.
Besok lusa aku sela setelah pukul 17.00.
I'll ask my husband.
Aku akan tanya suamiku.
That cheating man is all brawn and no brain.
Si peselingkuh itu cuma modal otot, otaknya kosong.
Please fix him up for me.
Tolong sembuhkan, Dok.
Doctor, you've finished your examinations for today.
Dok, pasien hari ini sudah habis.
Okay, you can go home now, Ms. Melles.
Baik, kau boleh pulang, Bu Melles.
I'll be off then.
Aku pamit dulu.
Also, Ms. Melles,
Bu Melles,
you forgot to lock the back door again yesterday.
kemarin kau lupa lagi mengunci pintu belakang.
Oh, no!
Astaga!
I almost forgot today too!
Hari ini juga hampir lupa!
I messed up again…
Lagi-lagi aku lupa…
Have a good night.
Terima kasih.
Hi, Dr. Gillen?
Halo, Dr. Gillen?
It's Reichwein.
Aku Reichwein.
I saw the newspaper.
Aku sudah baca koran.
Yeah, the ad you put in the papers.
Ya, iklan yang kau pasang di koran.
"Let's reminisce about how we cheated on that test. From Rudy."
"Mari kita kenang masa-masa menyontek saat ujian. Dari Rudy."
Will these words really get Dr. Tenma to contact you?
Dokter Tenma akan menghubungimu jika melihat iklan ini?
Yes, he definitely will if he sees it.
Pasti, jika dia melihatnya.
Well, it's a story only the two of us know.
Itu kisah unik kami berdua.
I see.
Begitu rupanya.
Doctor, don't do anything rash until he shows up.
Dr. Reichwein, jangan gegabah sebelum dia muncul.
I know.
Aku paham.
But there's one thing I want to look into.
Tapi ada satu hal yang ingin kuselidiki.
What is it?
Apa?
It's the prostitute who called herself Margot Langer.
Wanita tunasusila yang mengaku bernama Margot Langer.
Here's what Richard said.
Richard bilang begini.
When Fahren, who committed suicide, went to go see that woman,
Saat Fahren yang bunuh diri menemui perempuan itu,
there was another young man with him.
ada pemuda lain bersamanya.
An attractive young man with blond hair.
Pemuda tampan berambut pirang.
Be careful, Doctor.
Hati-hati.
I know.
Aku mengerti.
I'll move with great care now so we can expose everything.
Aku akan berhati-hati supaya semua ini bisa terbongkar.
For the deceased Richard as well.
Ini demi mendiang Richard juga.
Well then, I'll call you again later.
Baiklah, nanti kukabari lagi.
Ms. Melles, you forgot to close the window this time.
Bu Melles, kali ini kau lupa menutup jendela.
Margot Langer?
Margot Langer?
Don't know her.
Aku tak kenal.
Well, her nickname now should be Sophie or something of the sort.
Kalau tidak salah nama panggilannya sekarang Sophie, atau semacamnya.
Oh, that fat old woman, huh?
Bibi-bibi gemuk itu, ya?
Is that what you're into, old man?
Seleramu yang begitu?
No, that's not what I'm here for.
Bukan itu tujuanku kemari.
Embarrassed at this age?
Sudah tua masih malu-malu.
Turn at the second corner. It's the second floor of the old building.
Masuk di belokan kedua. Dia di lantai kedua gedung lama.
Thanks.
Terima kasih.
But she's not there.
Tapi dia tak ada.
What?
Apa?
I haven't seen her in a while.
Sudah lama tak kelihatan.
I bet she went somewhere nice.
Mungkin pergi ke tempat indah.
Somewhere nice?
Tempat indah?
Damn, why does that old hag get all the guys?
Kok bisa, sih, bibi-bibi itu digemari lelaki?
I heard a super-rich guy used to visit her until recently too.
Kudengar ada pria kaya raya yang sering mendatanginya.
Where'd she go?
Dia ke mana?
Hey, how about you try me out?
Hei, kau tak ingin coba bersamaku?
I'll give you a much better time than that old hag.
Aku lebih jago dari bibi-bibi itu.
Do you know where she went?
Kau tahu dia ke mana?
I don't know.
Tak tahu.
She probably went somewhere with that new guy.
Mungkin pergi dengan lelaki baru.
A new guy?
Lelaki baru?
Yeah.
Ya.
Instead of acting her age, she's head over heels for him.
Bukannya sadar umur, dia kesengsem oleh lelaki itu.
He's a huge man.
Pria besar.
A huge man?
Pria besar?
That guy looks like he'd be big down there too.
Sepertinya "barang"-nya juga besar.
Excuse me, Doctor.
Maaf, Dok.
Would it be okay if I clocked out for today?
Apa hari ini aku sudah boleh pulang?
Oh right, you work until five today.
Benar juga, hari ini sampai pukul 17.00, ya?
It's okay. I have one last appointment with the cheating husband.
Boleh saja. Jadwalku tinggal menemui suami tukang selingkuh.
It's a date, right, Ms. Melles?
Bu Melles mau kencan, 'kan?
Don't tease me, Doctor.
Ya ampun, Dok.
Make sure you lock up, okay?
Jangan lupa dikunci, ya?
The prostitute named Sophie who called herself Margot Langer.
Wanita tunasusila yang mengaku bernama Margot Langer.
I wanted to show her this photo
Kalau kutunjukkan foto ini
and have her testify that Johan was the young man with the deceased Fahren.
dan kuminta dia bersaksi Johan pernah datang bersama Fahren,
Then we would've been one step closer.
mungkin akan ada kemajuan di kasus ini.
Yes?
Ya?
I'm Hesse. My wife made me an appointment.
Aku Hesse. Istriku sudah buat janji.
Oh, yes. Please come in.
Baik. Silakan masuk.
Maybe I'll try and visit that woman again tonight.
Mungkin nanti malam kucoba datangi lagi perempuan itu.
Nice to meet you, Dr. Reichwein.
Salam kenal, Dr. Reichwein.
Welcome, Mr. Hesse.
Selamat datang, Pak Hesse.
I'll be in your care.
Mohon bantuannya.
Please come in.
Silakan masuk.
It's my first time receiving counseling.
Ini pertama kali aku konseling.
There's nothing to be nervous about.
Tidak perlu merasa gugup.
You can relax and talk about anything here.
Kau bisa bersantai dan mencurahkan apa saja di sini.
Anything said here will be strictly confidential,
Apa pun yang kau sampaikan di sini bersifat rahasia.
so please relax.
Jadi, tenang saja.
You won't tell my wife?
Dirahasiakan ke istriku?
Of course not.
Tentu saja.
How are you feeling lately?
Bagaimana perasaanmu belakangan?
Any worries?
Adakah yang kau cemaskan?
-Worries? -Yes.
- Cemas? - Ya.
My wife found out that I was cheating on her.
Aku dipergoki selingkuh oleh istriku.
Yes, I see.
Begitu.
I'm really bored when I'm at home,
Aku bosan sekali di rumah,
so I tidy up the yard and wash the car.
jadi aku merapikan taman dan mencuci mobil.
That's how I spend every day.
Itu kebiasaanku tiap hari.
Does it make you feel a bit better?
Kebiasaan itu melegakan bagimu?
No, I don't speak to my wife at all.
Tidak, aku tak bicara dengan istriku sama sekali.
Is it that you can't, even though you want to?
Meski ingin bicara, tapi tak bisa?
Well, I'm not sure.
Yah, entahlah.
What about the other woman?
Perempuan lainnya bagaimana?
What?
Apa?
Are you and the woman you cheated with no longer…
Kau dan selingkuhanmu sudah tak berhubungan?
No, I had a dream where I killed her.
Bukan, aku bermimpi membunuhnya.
Do you have that kind of dream often?
Kau sering bermimpi begitu?
Often?
Sering?
Well, I haven't had one recently.
Tidak, belakangan tak pernah.
I was lonely.
Dari dulu aku kesepian.
And that's why you cheated on your wife?
Itu sebabnya kau selingkuh?
No, it started when I met that man.
Tidak, awal mulanya saat aku bertemu pria itu.
That man?
Pria itu?
He's an attractive young man with blond hair.
Pemuda tampan berambut pirang.
No matter how many people I killed, and even when I lost my country,
Meski telah banyak yang kubunuh, meski negaraku runtuh,
it was all like a dream to me.
semuanya seperti hanya di angan-angan.
But it changed after I met him.
Tapi semua berubah setelah mengenal pemuda itu.
Everything looked real
Semuanya tampak nyata
and I was no longer lonely.
dan aku tak lagi kesepian.
Would you like some tea?
Mau minum teh?
No, I'm fine.
Tidak perlu, terima kasih.
I'm feeling a bit thirsty.
Aku agak haus.
Can you wait for a bit?
Tunggu sebentar, ya?
My secretary already left.
Sekretarisku sudah pulang.
I think it's a date.
Sepertinya kencan.
She makes tea so well.
Teh seduhan dia enak.
It's a shame I can't serve it to you.
Sayang kau tak bisa mencicipinya.
Doctor?
Doktor?
What is it?
Ada apa?
You see a lot in your line of work, don't you?
Kau psikolog, pasti sering mendengarnya, 'kan?
After all, you learn about people's dreams.
Karena tugasmu mendengarkan mimpi-mimpi orang.
Nothing good comes from learning about dreams you don't need to know.
Tak ada untungnya mengetahui impian yang bukan urusanmu.
Especially the fact that I'm a murderer.
Apalagi,
Anyway… if you have any inclination of starting over with your wife…
Omong-omong, kalau ingin memperbaiki hubungan dengan istrimu…
you need to speak with her again and…
cobalah diskusikan lagi…
I hope you forgot to lock the door, Ms. Melles.
Semoga kau lupa kunci pintu, Bu Melles.
You're…
Kau…
Hurry and run!
Cepat lari!
Dr. Tenma.
Dokter Tenma?
I've been guarding you.
Selama ini aku menjagamu.
They're targeting you. Run!
Mereka mengincarmu. Larilah!
Hurry!
Cepat!
In Broad Daylight
Terjemahan subtitle oleh Rizky Soraya